foreign
hi Jonathan it's Frank defreitis how are
you I'm well how are you good I was so
surprised this was the first
international call I dialed direct with
the new uh service that I have and it
went right through so I'm happy for that
no well I'm glad it's working uh why
don't we start off by you doing a
introduction to your gallery
in London how how that came about did
you have a gallery previous to the one
that you have now because I know we've
been in touch for many many years but I
had a gallery way back in in the late
1970s
it's called the Hologram place
that had the honor of being the first
specialist holographic Gallery in Europe
but it was also one of the shortest
running I should think we only managed
to keep going a year oh I see
um back then there was very little
the market
in any case and really the public didn't
know what to make of it either oh okay
I imagine it must have been some of the
early artists like Margaret Banyan and a
few of the other folks back then right
well Market was actually in Australia at
that time but we had
um pieces from uh don Schweitzer and
samurai oh okay and um that sort of
generation yeah the the same folks that
were exhibiting around that time at the
Museum of Photography in New York on
Mercer Street exactly I mean that's how
we all got ready thanks to the museum of
philosophy in New York yeah it was quite
this this was a personal vision of your
own right I've always heard the Jonathan
Ross holography collection or hologram
collection so this was your own personal
Vision right well at the beginning
um it wasn't
a bunch of people who'd learn about
holography a little longer than I had
um I I'd seen the light fantastic
exhibitions of the Royal Academy in
London which were the first
um firstly laser transmission and then
white light reflection Holograms to be
seen in England okay
um but I met this group of enthusiasts
who wanted to do something and I joined
up with them but I
preferably anyone still hanging in from
that lot yeah what what's the scene like
in specifically London with holography
right now well there are a number of
people doing command commercial work
there's um particularly the people at
spatial Imaging Rob Monday and Jeffrey
Robb and then there's Mike medora's
Company color holographics okay which is
making fantastic large format kind of
stereograms they're the new producers of
the BB plates as well right didn't they
buy the technology yeah but as far as
art goes there's um London's in a bit of
a quiet period uh
Patrick Boyd is hoping to open a school
of holography out of Richmond where
spatial Imaging are based okay but
that's still
um in the planning stage yeah he's been
here at my place when he's been in the
states yeah well that Patrick was at the
Royal College of Art here and I think
one of the most interesting of the
people to come out of that period yeah
you have more than holography in your
gallery though right
I I show holography maybe once a year or
every two years
um mainly I'm showing painted for two
reasons one is that there's so little
logography being being made in the UK
and they are
with some people aren't really aware of
it as a collectible art medium still to
this day huh I think people enjoy
looking at holography yeah when I have
it in the gallery they love the shows
but the idea of buying it hasn't quite
gone through have you ever done any work
with the schools
I've had an exhibition in one of the
London schools
and
the the over the years has been
um some educational uh activity in the
UK I mean Pearl John for instance is
teaching done in the Portsmouth at the
moment yes she was at a career center
here in the U.S for a number of years
yes yes and um actually she's going to
be giving a talk to the role
photographic Society next month about
her work there okay
[Applause]
um Martin Richardson is also doing some
teaching at the moment he's based at De
Montfort University
it's very popular here in the states for
what we have called science fairs with
the students you know
you know do you see that there as well
yeah uh some of the big exhibitions in
the past have been associated with
science
um institutions of one kind or another
like the science museum in London
but uh there really hasn't been a big
show here for a long time and I think
that's what's needed
certainly certainly that's where I'm
putting my energies into into um trying
to persuade a museum to to put on a
holography show now I noticed that your
holography shows are basically through
Invitation Only it's it's the same group
of people that usually come to your
openings or or is it an Ever expansive
group of people
it is expanding because my mailing list
increases and so show by show I add
names to it whether you live there right
yeah it's um all in my house which which
makes uh not having to go to work in the
morning a pleasure yeah same here I'm in
my own house I've had the holography lab
here for over 20 years and in my case it
helps because the folks that come here
to take holography workshops want to see
how it's done in a home
because they want to go back and do it
in their own home so it's a perfect
situation for them yeah
I used to have a holography lab in a
previous home
when I was involved with a company
called C3 Holograms and we were doing
mastering for emboss embossed Holograms
do you still do any Holograms
not personally no
um I sold my business in about 1990
um since then it's been more collecting
and exhibition organizing that I focused
on you know when we first started
corresponding it was through the mail
back and forth I I believe you were on a
mailing list for an old newsletter that
I started back in the early 80s called
the Hologram that I would mail out to
everyone I'd compile information and
send that out how is the web change
things for you now that you have the
website I notice you have two websites
you have the one specifically for your
gallery and then also another one that
leads over to a more holography related
website yes well let's open things up
fantastically I'm sure you'll find that
too I mean your your website it's a
great source of information for everyone
in the community but I I find I guess
that um I get inquiries from all over
the world now which I did to a certain
extent before but far more so I mean
it's usually from people who who are
asking for free catalog on my website
yeah and from everywhere you can think
of they describe themselves as being
interested photography for a number of
reasons so I might want to take it up I
imagine that's widened your geographical
area for people who come to your
openings as well right well I I wouldn't
say I get that many visitors from from
overseas I mean every now and again
someone will maybe
um be on a trip to London and come and
see the collection
you're located in a place in London
that's uh next to what is it called West
Kensington or New Kensington or
something
yeah it's part of um Kinston Chelsea and
Earl's Court where I am was historically
famous for its Australian Community
although that changed over the years it
used to be called kangaroo Valley over
here okay
yeah I I saw your uh
your gallery slash home on on your
website and we have similar homes it's
what we call here in the states similar
to a row home
I wish we call them row homes because
they're very close together they don't
have a lot of land around them you know
okay right yeah we call it a tariff over
here okay yeah yeah I grew up in an area
of Philadelphia called Kensington by the
way yeah
of
tell us a little bit about
your collection and some of the pieces
that you have do you still are you still
adding pieces to your collection or is
that pretty much
um there's a
core of office that I'm I'm interested
in and if they have um works but I've
always been interested to look at them
um the most recent piece I think I
acquired was a beautiful oh
period Rudy Burkhart
um one called breakthrough which he
exhibited in his Whitney Museum show
okay
but um
that's a kind of a rare occurrence
to bring something in from the states
yeah yeah I bought a piece of Dan
schweitzer's after he died from his
widow which was another Beauty called
seed okay oh yes yes I've I've seen that
hologram in New York well I I remember
seeing it the first time I went to visit
salmon dance studio in New York when I
did a short course there in about 1980
and I think that Dana just made that
hologram and it really blew my mind I
couldn't work out how he'd made it of
course he was going to tell me but it
always stayed in my mind and um we
discussed it over the years uh but I
could never really afford it until just
recently do you have any pseudo color
Reflections in your collection
yeah certainly quite quite by quite a
John Kaufman was probably one of them
I've been buying from
um over the years I had a one-man show
that is here in fact um a few years ago
Sanders I think he's not producing any
longer do you ever display any laser
transmission Holograms
I have once only once um and that was
quite recently because I had here in
London called Mike Anderson make me a
little laser diode display
using a small diode and an overhead
mirror to control the light
it worked very well I showed um
I showed one of Margaret banyan's early
pieces
and actually and then I showed a little
piece that Paula Dawson gave me to
I think Margaret bennion was the first
person that I had seen a holography show
of in New York and she had a lot of
laser transmission pieces there at the
time and I love them except that for the
fact that the regulations are getting so
strict
anymore for uh displaying any large
format
laser transmission Holograms that you
don't see them around too much anymore
outside of you know demonstrations and
things like that at a score or a lab
yes I expect that's right I mean I
remember the first Holograms I saw uh at
the Royal Academy were laser
transmission and they had these black
and gray argon lasers with
to illuminate them
um they've actually made a feature of
the laser running a lot along the
ceiling of the gallery before being
beamed down onto the plate they look
great but I haven't seen anything like
that in a long time either I'm going to
have a link that'll go directly to your
website I'll send them right over to
your gallery website and that'll be on
the whole talk page for a while either
while they're listening to the show or
after the show is over they can go and
visit what you've been doing
well that would be good I'm not I have
to um mention Andy Pepper when you
mentioned the website because Andy was
the person who put me up for having a
site in the first place ever since yeah
that's a very nice site beautiful job I
think yeah it's a beautiful site it's a
beautiful layout very nice and clean
it's very clean
well we we change it from time to time
and is working on some new things at the
moment
I haven't got too much
um video on it but a few little clips
might try and add some more of those
what are your plans for the future do
you ever take your collection on the
road it would be nice to have it touring
the states don't you think well I did
one show in the states I'm a very small
one I had to go the The Butler Institute
of American art yes that's right that
was in Ohio that's right yeah they've
shown a lot of Photography since then
um the director there uh luzona was
responsible for opening up this new wing
of the gallery which is all to do with
meteor art and technology and
um he's shown I think well Andy pepper
Patrick Boyd
um I think
some of the New York artists as well
he's um he's very supportive
but I haven't got anything else lined up
in the states for now but always open to
invitations yeah yeah
oh I saw your curious cabinet that's
interesting I I collect a lot of stuff
like that for holography too I have tons
of stuff like that that's in your
curious cabinet I think it's
irresistible um yeah the internet
certainly
helped me in that respect because now
that eBay is there you can just find
endless holographic knickknacks yeah and
stuff that that um I'd probably let by
go by or wasn't available in England at
the time some of the toys and
holographic CDs and packaging and stuff
like that I think it's well worth
collecting yeah I one of one of my
pieces that I really cherish I have a
number of them uh maybe about four or
five of them left it's uh from what I
understand probably one of the first
commercial uses of holography was the
king vitamin ring oh yeah I think that
was the little red plastic ring with um
a reflection hologram on the top yeah it
was the McDonald Douglas pulse laser
that did those
and it's got King vitamin it's got a
little secret chamber in it and you can
wear the ring and it's an image plane
reflection hologram rather dim
but image plane reflection hologram of
King vitamin wearing the crown and he
sort of sticks out of the ring you know
if you get it aligned properly but it's
a nice little piece in that realm anyway
well I picked one of those up when I
visited the Museum of Photography yeah
but but um I've never seen the real
packaging I've seen it reproduced you
don't have um the original cereal box
here oh no I do not no that would be
nice to have wouldn't it
all that kind of stuff I think people
will um still enjoy in the years to come
don't you I I think so I think so and
and just for the fact that it's a
curiosity more than anything else
how do you feel about amateur and
hobbyist telegraphy do you uh follow
that at all well I'm always interested
to see
programs that people
a few people that attend uh raw
photographic Society meetings who are
trying to do the Holograms in a small
way and um I'm very supportive of what
they do uh it's probably bigger in the
states more of you over there yeah
certainly some of the early holographers
uh produce their work on very
inexpensive equipment didn't they I mean
yeah little five milliwatt lasers and
sand tables and all of that yeah yeah
what are your plans for the future with
the gallery
well um I do art first occasionally to
try and broaden my audience but
otherwise I just uh do six to eight
shows a year show holography when I can
and um I've got a little stable of
English painters so I'm promoting them
and just rolls on really yeah and
is the is the gallery your
main career is that what you do for your
career as uh art and and gallery these
days I mean I
um I would say holography is still one
of my main interests but uh the gallery
probably absorbs more time than I can
spend on on holography per se yeah you
have a videotape as well don't you I
remember getting a flyer or something in
the mailbox video years ago a guy called
Matthew Andrews produced and I um
finance that that's quite a while ago
now but but he was doing some
educational stuff and he needed a a
video
um to show in classrooms so he made a
this seven minute tape called how to
make a hologram and it's it's a good
introduction I think yeah
that be ordered from your website as
well yeah there's still copies of that
available is that is that in a format
CD-ROM last year oh really The
Collection oh okay I'm gonna send you a
copy of that if you don't have it enough
please do
um is the video tape
available in a format I imagine there's
there's a pal format or um ntse okay
great all right well we'll get the
notice out about the new show and people
can come online and hear about you and
your gallery and some of the history
behind it and then go over to your
website and check it out do you have a
mailing list that people can subscribe
to as well on the website uh you can
subscribe for uh updates so when site
gets changed you'll get a notification
and if anybody wants to email me with
any inquiries or
assisted to correspond on the subject
level review I'm always pleased to hear
from anyone in
one end yeah I believe I'm on that list
because I get your email notifications
and I appreciate that
and Jonathan it's really been great
talking to you it's been so many years
and uh
always remember your
um your newsletter with the little
silhouette of the man in the deer
Stroker with the merchant pipe oh yeah
yeah that does go back
yeah well I was always a 221B Baker
Street uh fanatic at one time so have
you ever been to London no I have not
uh it's something I need to do at some
point if I can get myself onto an
airplane which I don't fly so that's
really Limited uh my involvement uh
personally emotion liner and I'll um
look forward to seeing you sometime an
ocean liner might not be a bad idea
Jonathan thank you so much
it was great it was great talking to you
take care all right bye bye